{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Of the following the busiest oceanic trade route is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cape route ",
            "optionB": "  North Atlantic route ",
            "optionC": "  Panama canal ",
            "optionD": "  Suez canal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOf the following the busiest oceanic trade route is North Atlantic route. It connects the South America to North America(Panama Canal), Africa to Europe and Europe to Asia (through Gibraltar Strait connecting Mediterranean Sea ). It is the trade route between the continents and is always full of cargo ships being carried around continent to page on continent. ",
            "keyString": "445735s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is world's deepest trench \"Mariana Trench\" located?",
            "optionA": "  In Indian Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  In Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "   In Arctic Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  In Pacific Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMariana Trench is located in the western Pacific Ocean, it is considered to be the deepest part of the Earth\u2019s surface. In fact, it is the Challenger Deep in the Mariana Trench that is known as the deepest point.",
            "keyString": "445766s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The average salinity of the sea water is ________ parts per thousand.",
            "optionA": "  25 ",
            "optionB": "  35 ",
            "optionC": "  50 ",
            "optionD": "  60 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe average salinity of the sea water is 35 parts per thousand. The average ocean salinity is 35 ppt and the average river water salinity is 0.5 ppt or less. This means that in every kilogram (1000 grams) of seawater, 35 grams are salt.",
            "keyString": "445780s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers falls into the Atlantic Ocean?\n1. Orinoco\n2. Danube\n3. Amazon\n4. Congo",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrinoco, Amazon and Congo rivers falls into the Atlantic Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "445793s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sargasso sea is located in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  North Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  North Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  North Sea ",
            "optionD": "  South Atlantic Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sargasso Sea is a huge patch of ocean that is completely surrounded by water on all sides. It\u2019s located within the North Atlantic subtropical gyre and is surrounded by strong currents, which makes it the only sea in the world that doesn\u2019t have a land boundary. ",
            "keyString": "445808s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Marine cliffs are formed mainly due to",
            "optionA": "  Ocean Currents ",
            "optionB": "  Structure of Shall ",
            "optionC": "  Coast of Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Depth of The Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Marine cliffs are formed mainly due to Ocean Currents. Moving water works as degradational agent (erosional). As oceanic currents move constantly in their definite path. They erode away rock against which they strike. ",
            "keyString": "493034s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hawaiian islands are located in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  North Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  South Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  North Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  South Pacific Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main Hawaiian Islands are a group of inhabited islands situated in the northern Pacific Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "493114s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Victoria Falls in Africa are located on ________ ",
            "optionA": "  River Niger ",
            "optionB": "  River Congo ",
            "optionC": "  River Zambezi ",
            "optionD": "  River Nile ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVictoria Falls is one of the greatest attractions in Africa and one of the most spectacular waterfalls in the world, Victoria Falls is located on the Zambezi River, the fourth largest river in Africa, which is also defining the border between Zambia and Zimbabwe. ",
            "keyString": "493162s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Atlantic Ocean routes are busier than the Pacific Ocean routes because Atlantic Ocean ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Routes are shorter ",
            "optionB": "  Routes are not so dangerous ",
            "optionC": "  Is surrounded on both sides by industrialised nations ",
            "optionD": "  Has better shipping facilities ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Atlantic Ocean routes are busier than the Pacific Ocean routes because Atlantic Ocean is surrounded on both sides by industrialised nations. The Atlantic ocean is the second largest ocean basin only behind the pacific ocean.Its bounded by North and South Americas in the west and Africa and Europe in the east. It also boasts of being the busiest ocean in the world. ",
            "keyString": "493199s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following currents is produced by upwelling of water off the coast of Chile and Peru?",
            "optionA": "  Canarie Current ",
            "optionB": "  Humboldt Current ",
            "optionC": "  Benguela Current ",
            "optionD": "  Kuroshio Current ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Humboldt Current, also known as the Peru Current, is an ocean current that flows along the western coast of South America, affecting the water and air temperatures of coastal Chile and Peru. ",
            "keyString": "493234s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Niagara Falls are in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Australia ",
            "optionB": "  U.K. ",
            "optionC": "  South Africa ",
            "optionD": "  U.S.",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNiagara Falls are in U.S.A. Niagara Falls is a city on the Niagara River, in New York State. It\u2019s known for the vast Niagara Falls, which straddle the Canadian border. In Niagara Falls State Park, the Observation Tower, at Prospect Point, juts out over Niagara Gorge for a view of all 3 waterfalls. ",
            "keyString": "535498s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest lake above the sea level in the world is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lake Avernus ",
            "optionB": "  Lake Tanzania ",
            "optionC": "  Lake Toba ",
            "optionD": "  Lake Titicaca ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe highest commercially navigable lake is Lake Titicaca, which lies in the Altiplano at a height of 3,810 m (12,500 ft) above sea level on the Andean border between Peru and Bolivia. ",
            "keyString": "600523s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The longest inland waterways in the world is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Mississippi river system ",
            "optionB": "  The Great Lakes ",
            "optionC": "  St. Lawrence ",
            "optionD": "  River Rhine ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMississippi River, the longest river of North America, draining with its major tributaries an area of approximately 1.2 million square miles (3.1 million square km), or about one-eighth of the entire continent. ",
            "keyString": "600581s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest and the busiest inland waterways in the world is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  R. Rhine in Germany ",
            "optionB": "  R. Ganga in India ",
            "optionC": "  The Great Lakes and the rivers St. Lawrence in U.SA ",
            "optionD": "  R. Lena and Lake Baikal in Russia ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest and the busiest inland waterways in the world is The Great Lakes and the rivers St. Lawrence in U.S.A. The Great Lakes\u2013St. Lawrence system, the other half of the midcontinental inland waterway, is connected to the Mississippi\u2013Ohio via Chicago by canals and the Illinois River. ",
            "keyString": "600596s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest island in the Indian Ocean is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Madagascar ",
            "optionB": "  Maldives ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionD": "  Sumatra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadagascar is the largest island with an area of about 226,658 square miles. Madagascar is located in the Indian Ocean 250 miles off the eastern coast of Africa across the Mozambique Channel, just south of the equator. ",
            "keyString": "600611s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The World's largest shipping canal is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Suez in Egypt ",
            "optionB": "  Panama in America ",
            "optionC": "  Kiel in Germany ",
            "optionD": "  Gota in Sweden ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLongest Canal in World is Suez Canal. The Suez Canal, located in Egypt, is a 101 mile (163 km) long canal. ",
            "keyString": "600628s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these statements are correct?\n1. Ocean currents are the slow- surface movement of water in the ocean.\n2. Ocean currents assist in maintaining the Earth's heat balance.\n3. Ocean currents are set in motion primarily by prevailing winds.\n4. Ocean currents are affected by the configuration of the ocean.",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 3, and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 3, and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the statements are correct. Ocean currents are the slow-surface movement of water in the ocean. Ocean currents assist in maintaining the Earth's heat balance. Ocean currents are set in motion primarily by prevailing winds. Ocean currents are affected by the configuration of the ocean. ",
            "keyString": "647733s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following sequences of ocean trenches is correct in terms of the ascending order of their depths?",
            "optionA": "  Aleutian Trench - Mindanao Trench - New Hebrides Trench ",
            "optionB": "  New Hebrides Trench - Mindanao Trench - Aleutian Trench ",
            "optionC": "  Aleutian Trench - New Hebrides Trench - Mindanao Trench ",
            "optionD": "  New Hebrides Trench - Aleutian Trench - Mindanao Trench ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following sequences of ocean trenches that is correct in terms of the ascending order of their depths are New Herbides Trench - Aleutian Trench - Mindanao Trench. New Hebrides Trench reaches maximum depths of some 25,000 feet (7,600 metres) or more, the deepest soundings in the whole Coral Sea region. The Aleutian Trench reaches a maximum depth of 26,604 feet (8,109 metres) at about 51\u00b0 N, 178\u00b0 W.The Mindanao trench reaches one of the greatest depths in the ocean, third only to the Mariana trench and the Tonga trench. Its deepest point is known as Galathea Depth and reaches 10,540 meters (34,580 ft) or (5,760 fathoms). ",
            "keyString": "647833s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following rivers is the longest?",
            "optionA": "  Amazon ",
            "optionB": "  Amur ",
            "optionC": "  Congo ",
            "optionD": "  Volga ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Amazon is considered the world's largest river by volume, but scientists have believed it is slightly shorter than Africa's Nile. The Brazilian scientists' 14-day expedition extended the Amazon's length by about 176 miles (284 kilometers), making it 65 miles (105 kilometers) longer than the Nile. ",
            "keyString": "647865s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Along the coasts salinity is",
            "optionA": "  Lowered ",
            "optionB": "  Increased ",
            "optionC": "  Stable ",
            "optionD": "  Unaffected ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlong the coasts salinity is lowered. Salinity in the oceans is constant but is more variable along the coast where seawater is diluted with freshwater from runoff or from the emptying of rivers. ",
            "keyString": "647890s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following lake is known as \"Honeymoon Lake\"?",
            "optionA": "  Nyasa ",
            "optionB": "  Chad ",
            "optionC": "  Titicaca ",
            "optionD": "  Toba ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLake Titicaca is called as 'Honeymoon Lake'. Lake Titicaca is famous among honeymoon couples due to its scenic features. Situated in Andes range it marks border of Bolivia & Peru. It is large & deep lake. The largest in South America. ",
            "keyString": "647918s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is a type of erosion caused by hydraulic action?",
            "optionA": "  Flowing Water ",
            "optionB": "  Wind ",
            "optionC": "   Glacier ",
            "optionD": "  None Of These ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFlowing Water is a type of erosion caused by hydraulic action. Hydraulic action is the erosion that occurs when the motion of water against a rock surface produces mechanical weathering. Most generally, it is the ability of moving water to dislodge and transport rock particles. ",
            "keyString": "689669s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about rain water harvesting?",
            "optionA": "  It is helpful in raising water level ",
            "optionB": "  It increases the harms of flow ",
            "optionC": "  It is a mode of water conservation ",
            "optionD": "  It is helpful in fulfilling the growing demands\nof water ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Harms of flow\" means surface run off of water during rainy season in plain region which leads to eroding away of surface layer of soil where as rain water harvesting avoids such occurrences. ",
            "keyString": "689711s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Temperature of surface water is comparatively higher in the northern hemisphere than in the southern hemisphere.\n2. The isotherms in the southern hemisphere are not regular and do not follow the latitudes while they (isotherms) are regular and follow the latitudes in the northern hemisphere.\nWhich of the statement(s) given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTemperature of surface water is comparatively higher in the northern hemisphere than in the southern hemisphere. The temperature of ocean water varies in the northern and the southern hemispheres because of dominance of land in the former and water in the latter. The oceans in the northern hemisphere receive more heat due to their contact with larger extent of land than their counter\u00adparts in the southern hemisphere and thus the tempera\u00adture of surface water is comparatively higher in the former than the latter. ",
            "keyString": "689725s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. On the planet Earth, the fresh water available for use amounts to about less than 1% of the total water found.\n2. Of the total fresh water found on the planet Earth, 95% is bound up in polar ice caps and glaciers.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe earth has an abundance of water, but unfortunately, only a small percentage (about 0.3%), is even usable by humans. The majority of total freshwater on Earth, about 68.7%, is held in ice caps and glaciers. ",
            "keyString": "689742s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\nI. Suez Canal is an important link between developed countries and developing countries.\nII. It joins the Mediterranean Sea with the Gulf of Suez\nIII. It is not a sea level canal.\nWhich of the statement given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I and III ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  I only ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSuez Canal is an important link between developed countries and developing countries and it joins the Mediterranean Sea with the Gulf of Suez. ",
            "keyString": "689757s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One will have to pass through the Suez Canal while going from Bombay to ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Alexandria ",
            "optionB": "  Suez ",
            "optionC": "  Port Said ",
            "optionD": "  Benghazi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne will not have to pass through the Suez Canal while going from Bombay to Suez. ",
            "keyString": "737085s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the correct sequence of the four stages of water movement in a hydrological cycle?",
            "optionA": "  Evaporation \u2013 Condensation \u2013 Precipitation \u2013 Infiltration ",
            "optionB": "  Evaporation \u2013 Precipitation \u2013 Condensation \u2013 Infiltration ",
            "optionC": "  Infiltration \u2013 Evaporation \u2013 Condensation \u2013 Infiltration ",
            "optionD": "  Condensation \u2013 Precipitation \u2013 Evaporation \u2013 Infiltration ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOf the many processes involved in the water cycle, the most important are Evaporation \u2013 Condensation \u2013 Precipitation \u2013 Infiltration. ",
            "keyString": "737114s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A wide inlet of the sea usually concave in shape, is termed as a",
            "optionA": "  Strait ",
            "optionB": "  Sound ",
            "optionC": "  Bay ",
            "optionD": "  Fjord ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDue to action of water, inundation of shoreline takes place and such an inundation with a wide inlet and concave shape is called bay. Example- Hudson Bey. ",
            "keyString": "737127s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which set of two rivers form the world's largest delta before their waters flows into the respective sea?",
            "optionA": "  Rhine - Seine ",
            "optionB": "  Nile - Euphrates ",
            "optionC": "  Ganges - Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Danube - Thames ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRiver Ganga and river Brahmaputra make the largest river delta of the World. Its a combined delta ever increasing as the two keep pouring more and more sediments into the sea. New islands keep appearing every year. ",
            "keyString": "737137s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The lake Ontario and St. Lawrence of USA and Canada lie to the south-east of",
            "optionA": "  Hudson Bay ",
            "optionB": "  Labrador Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  New Found land ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe lake Ontario and St. Lawrence of USA and Canada lie to the south-east of Hudson Bay. Lake Ontario is located on the border of the US and Canada. It borders the US states of New York and the Canadian province Ontario. ",
            "keyString": "737148s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest known ocean depth (which lies in the Pacific Ocean) is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  8,890 m ",
            "optionB": "  9,653 m ",
            "optionC": "  10,589 m ",
            "optionD": "  11,021 m ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"The deepest point in the ocean is generally believed to be in the Marianas Trench in the Western Pacific Ocean at approximately 36,160 feet (11,021 m), according to the Rand McNally Atlas (1977).\" ",
            "keyString": "783969s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following best explains the reason for the eastern and western boundaries of the Pacific Ocean experiencing frequent earthquake?",
            "optionA": "  There are deep ocean trenches along these margins ",
            "optionB": "  High mountain stretch along the continental margins adjacent to this ocean ",
            "optionC": "  The currents of the vast Pacific Ocean continue to dash against the continental margins ",
            "optionD": "  These margins coincide with the plate margins ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThese margins coincide with the plate margins best explains the reason for the eastern and western boundaries of the Pacific Ocean experiencing frequent earthquake. ",
            "keyString": "784004s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oceanic current named as 'Kuroshio - Kurile and Alaskan' are located in",
            "optionA": "  North Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  South Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  North Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  North Indian Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oceanic current named as 'Kuroshio - Kurile and Alaskan' are located in North Pacific Ocean.",
            "keyString": "784021s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following cities is associated with the river Mekong ?",
            "optionA": "  Hong Kong ",
            "optionB": "  Phnom-Penh ",
            "optionC": "  Shanghai ",
            "optionD": "  Yangon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhnom-Penh cities is associated with the river Mekong. The river flows through Laos, Cambodia, and Vietnam before draining into the South China Sea south of Ho Chi Minh City (formerly Saigon). Vientiane (Viangchan), the capital of Laos, and Phnom Penh, the capital of Cambodia, both stand on its banks. ",
            "keyString": "784036s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important navigable river in, Central Europe that provides a link between seven countries-Austria, Belgium, Czech Republic, Hungary, Rome, Russia and Yugoslavia is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Volga ",
            "optionB": "  Rhine ",
            "optionC": "  Dnieper ",
            "optionD": "  Danube ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important navigable river in, Central Europe that provides a link between seven countries-Austria, Belgium, Czech Republic, Hungary, Rome, Russia and Yugoslavia is Danube. ",
            "keyString": "784049s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The world's largest lake is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lake Victoria ",
            "optionB": "  Lake Superior ",
            "optionC": "  Caspian Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Black Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe world's largest lake is Caspian Sea. The salty Caspian Sea has the greatest surface area of any lake at 143,200 square miles (370,886 square kilometers). ",
            "keyString": "832777s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest sea in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Caspian Sea ",
            "optionB": "  South China Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionD": "  North Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, encompassing an area from the Karimata and Malacca Straits to the Strait of Taiwan. South China sea supports about one-third of the world\u2019s shipping transportation which carries over $3 trillion in trade each year. It is one of the largest seas in the world. ",
            "keyString": "832811s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fishing grounds in the Pacific Ocean, the world's greatest fishing regions, lie between the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Bering Sea and the Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionB": "  The North Sea and the Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionC": "  The East China Sea and the Bering Sea ",
            "optionD": "  The Mediterranean Sea and the Arabian Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt stretches from the Bering Sea to East China Sea and the world's largest as well as greatest fishing ground. ",
            "keyString": "832826s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following is Malta located?",
            "optionA": "  Baltic Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Black Sea ",
            "optionD": "  North Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe island of Malta is a small independent nation state that is located in the centre of the Mediterranean in Europe and is the EU's smallest member state. ",
            "keyString": "832838s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The equator cuts through which of the following islands ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Madagascar ",
            "optionB": "  Tasmania ",
            "optionC": "  Java ",
            "optionD": "  Borneo ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe island of Borneo is the largest island of the Malay archipelago and the third-largest island in the world, covering 287,420 square mi (736,974 square km). The equator cuts directly across the island, and its vegetation reflects this geographic position. ",
            "keyString": "832850s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The World's major commercial fishing grounds are located in the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cool waters of the northern hemisphere in comparatively higher latitudes ",
            "optionB": "  Equatorial water ",
            "optionC": "  Temperate waters of tropical seas ",
            "optionD": "  Warm water of seas in southern hemisphere ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe World's Ocean Fishing grounds are located in the cool waters of the northern hemisphere because in southern hemisphere commercial ocean fishing is less developed and best fishing grounds founded above continental shelves. ",
            "keyString": "877867s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The islands of Seychelles are located in the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Arctic Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  Pacific Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeychelles, island republic in the western Indian Ocean, comprising about 115 islands, with lush tropical vegetation, beautiful beaches, and a wide variety of marine life.",
            "keyString": "877906s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the correct sequence of the following topographical features found from upper to lower course of a river?",
            "optionA": "  Ox-bow lake-Rapids-Estuary ",
            "optionB": "  Rapids-Estuary-Ox-bow lake ",
            "optionC": "  Rapids- Ox-bow lake - Estuary ",
            "optionD": "  Estuary- Ox-bow lake-Rapids ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRapids-Ox-bow lake-Estuary. Rapids are sections of a river where the river bed has a relatively steep gradient, causing an increase in water velocity and turbulence. An oxbow lake is a U-shaped lake that forms when a wide meander from the main stem of a river is cut off, creating a free-standing body of water. An estuary is a partially enclosed coastal body of brackish water with one or more rivers or streams flowing into it, and with a free connection to the open sea. ",
            "keyString": "877924s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main part of water in coastal areas of ocean which is located near the main region of continents are called",
            "optionA": "  Topography ",
            "optionB": "  Ocean Peak ",
            "optionC": "  Continental Shelf ",
            "optionD": "  Continental Slope ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main part of water in coastal areas of ocean which is located near the main region of continents are called Continental Shelf. Continental shelf is one of the features of continental landmass submerged under shallow sea water. Its average widths is approximately 80km, and depth varies to about 150m. ",
            "keyString": "877940s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cities is incorrectly matched to the river on which it is situated?",
            "optionA": "  Budapest - River Danube ",
            "optionB": "  Baghad - River Tigris ",
            "optionC": "  Amsterdam - River Amsel ",
            "optionD": "  Alexandria - River Niger ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Niger rises in Guinea at 9\u00b005\u2032 N and 10\u00b047\u2032 W on the eastern side of the Fouta Djallon (Guinea) highlands, only 150 miles (240 km) inland from the Atlantic Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "877954s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Panama Canal links ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Mediterranean Sea with Red Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Atlantic Ocean with Indian Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Ocean with Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Atlantic Ocean with Pacific Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Panama Canal is a waterway that connects the Atlantic and the Pacific Ocean. Before the canal was opened in 1914 ships had to travel around the southern tip of South America to get from the Atlantic to the Pacific Ocean. The Panama Canal shortens the journey by about 11000 km. The Panama Canal is 82 km long. ",
            "keyString": "934095s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following oceans is Diamantina Trench situated?",
            "optionA": "  Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  Arctic Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Diamantina Trench is a deep sea trench in the South East Indian Basin. With a maximum depth of 8,047 meters, it is the deepest trench of the Indian Ocean, deeper than the better-known Java Trench. ",
            "keyString": "934130s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A narrow strip of land bordered on both sides by water, connecting two large bodies of land is known as ________ ",
            "optionA": "  An isthmus ",
            "optionB": "  A lagoon ",
            "optionC": "  A peninsula ",
            "optionD": "  A strait ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA narrow piece of land that connects two landmasses is known as an isthmus. It is generally surrounded by water bodies on two of its sides. ",
            "keyString": "934147s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following, which capital city is not situated on the banks of the river Danube?",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  Rome ",
            "optionC": "  Budapest ",
            "optionD": "  Belgrade ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRome is not situated on the banks of the river Danube. The Danube River flows directly through many significant European cities, including four national capitals \u2013 Vienna (Austria), Bratislava (Slovakia), Budapest (Hungary) and Belgrade (Serbia). It originates in Germany\u2019s Black Forest, and flows in a southeasterly direction through central and eastern Europe to the black sea. ",
            "keyString": "934161s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest river of the Asia?",
            "optionA": "  Indus River ",
            "optionB": "  Yangtze River ",
            "optionC": "  Hwang Ho River ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga River ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Yangtze River in China is the longest river in Asia, the third longest river in the world and the longest river to flow entirely in one country. ",
            "keyString": "934174s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which factors influence ocean currents?\nI. Coriolis force\nII. Local winds\nIII. Waves\nIV. Continent shape",
            "optionA": "  I and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe factors that influence ocean currents are Coriolis force, Waves and Continent shape. ",
            "keyString": "983012s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest delta of the World is",
            "optionA": "  Nippon Delta ",
            "optionB": "  Sicily Delta ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga Delta ",
            "optionD": "  Caspian Delta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGanga delta is one of World's most fertile deltas constituted by river Ganga & Brahmaputra in the east of India. Forming Bangladesh Plains, it is also known as Sunderban delta & Ganga - Brahmaputra delta. It is also called Green delta because of its fertility. ",
            "keyString": "983183s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Coast of Norway is an example of",
            "optionA": "  Dalmatian Coast ",
            "optionB": "  Fjord Coast ",
            "optionC": "   Ria Coast ",
            "optionD": "  Pelagic Coast ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Coast of Norway is an example of Fjord Coast. The fjords were formed by the giant glacier tongues that through several ice ages have shaped the landscape. A fjord is thus a U-shaped undersea valley, and on the west coast, this valley is often surrounded by dramatic mountain scenery. ",
            "keyString": "983283s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find the odd",
            "optionA": "  Dead Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Red Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Black Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Caspian Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn terms of salinity, the water of Dead Sea is highly saline when being compared to the other 3 given options. ",
            "keyString": "983416s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ring of Fire is found commonly in",
            "optionA": "  Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  Arctic Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRing of Fire is found commonly in Pacific Ocean. The Ring of Fire is a ring of volcanoes around the Pacific Ocean that result from subduction of oceanic plates beneath lighter continental plates. ",
            "keyString": "983498s28m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Niagara Falls is located between which of the following pairs of lakes?",
            "optionA": "  Lake Superior and Lake Huron ",
            "optionB": "  Lake Huron and Lake Erie ",
            "optionC": "  Lake Erie and Lake Ontario ",
            "optionD": "  Lake Ontario and Lake Huron ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe waterfalls of Niagara Falls are located on the Niagara River which connects two of the five Great Lakes, Lake Erie and Lake Ontario. Collectively the waterfalls are named Niagara Falls. They consist of three different waterfalls. The American Falls and the Bridal Veil Falls in the USA and the Canadian \u201cHorseshoe\u201d Falls in Canada. ",
            "keyString": "82605s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Dogger Bank, the main fishing area of Europe, lies in",
            "optionA": "  Baltic Sea ",
            "optionB": "  English Channel ",
            "optionC": "  North Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Norwegian Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dogger Bank, the main fishing area of Europe, lies in North Sea. For centuries it has been a well-known fishing ground. The large amounts of food available to the fish result in the catch of sizable quantities of plaice, cod, haddock, turbot, dabs, and herring.",
            "keyString": "82640s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why are major fishing areas of the world confined to the temperate zone?\nI. Cold and warm currents meet, creating conditions favourable for plankton growth\nII. The fish of these waters are highly palatable as human food\nIII. There is a ready mark, in the land masses of the zone\nIV. The existence of submarine plateaus help in growth of fish population",
            "optionA": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionB": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionC": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major fishing areas of the world confined to the temperate zone are Cold and warm currents meet, creating conditions favourable for plankton growth, The fish of these waters are highly palatable as human food, There is a ready mark, in the land masses of the zone and The existence of submarine plateaus help in growth of fish population. ",
            "keyString": "82656s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following connects the ocean floor level with the continental level ?",
            "optionA": "  Continental slope ",
            "optionB": "  Continental shelf ",
            "optionC": "  Epicontinental sea ",
            "optionD": "  Sea shelf ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tContinental slope connects the ocean floor level with the continental level. A continental shelf typically extends from the coast to depths of 100\u2013200 metres (330\u2013660 feet). It is gently inclined seaward at an average slope of about 0.1\u00b0. In nearly all instances, it ends at its seaward edge with an abrupt drop called the shelf break.",
            "keyString": "82676s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the ocean is Sargasso Sea?",
            "optionA": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  Arctic Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt lies within the Northern Atlantic Subtropical Gyre . The Gulf Stream establishes the Sargasso Sea's western boundary, while the Sea is further defined to the north by the North Atlantic Current, to the east by the Canary Current, and to the south by the North Atlantic Equatorial Current. ",
            "keyString": "82689s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following city is located on the banks of river Potomac?",
            "optionA": "  Berlin ",
            "optionB": "  Madrid ",
            "optionC": "  Islamabad ",
            "optionD": "  Washington ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPotomac river is a river in United States of America which drains an area of about 14,700 square miles andempties into Chesapeake Bay. Washington, D.C., is the capital city of the United States, located between Virginia and Maryland on the north bank of the Potomac River.",
            "keyString": "141197s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the smallest among the following water bodies?",
            "optionA": "  Arctic Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Hudson Bay ",
            "optionC": "  Japan Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Okhotsk Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sea of Japan is the marginal sea between the Japanese archipelago, Sakhalin, the Korean Peninsula and Russia, is the smallest among the following water bodies. ",
            "keyString": "141233s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following conditions are not favourable for the growth of coral reefs ?",
            "optionA": "  Sediment free water ",
            "optionB": "  Fresh water ",
            "optionC": "  Moderate saline water ",
            "optionD": "  Disturbed water and currents ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFresh water are not favourable for the growth of coral reefs. Coral require fairly good amount of sunlight to survive. The ideal depths for coral growth are 45 m to 55 m below sea surface, where there is abundant sunlight available. Clear salt water: Clear salt water is suitable for coral growth, while both fresh water and highly saline water are harmful. ",
            "keyString": "141251s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among these Islands has coral reef?",
            "optionA": "  Aleutian ",
            "optionB": "  Hawaiian ",
            "optionC": "  Andaman and Nicobar ",
            "optionD": "  Falklands Island ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe state of Hawaii consists of eight larger islands (seven of which are populated), also called the Main Hawaiian Islands, and 124 small, uninhabited islands, reefs and shoals, the Northwestern Hawaiian Islands, where the majority of the Hawaiian coral reef, about 70% of it, is located. ",
            "keyString": "141265s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which river has the largest drainage basin?",
            "optionA": "  Nile ",
            "optionB": "  Mississippi ",
            "optionC": "  Congo ",
            "optionD": "  Amazon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Amazon basin is the largest drainage basin in the world, with an area of approximately 7,050,000 square kilometres (2,720,000 sq mi). ",
            "keyString": "141278s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The melting down of glacier is normal event regarding the rising sea level. Most of the glaciers are found in",
            "optionA": "  Green Land ",
            "optionB": "  South Pole ",
            "optionC": "  Himalaya ",
            "optionD": "  North Pole ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the world\u2019s glaciers are found near the poles. Antarctica, thesouthernmost continent is filled of ice in form of vast glacier. The Antarctica lies in South Pole. ",
            "keyString": "205111s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest ocean is",
            "optionA": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  Arctic Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  Pacific Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Pacific Ocean is the largest and deepest of the world ocean basins. Covering approximately 63 million square miles and containing more than half of the free water on Earth, the Pacific is by far the largest of the world's ocean basins. All of the world's continents could fit into the Pacific basin. ",
            "keyString": "205334s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The salinity of the sea is maximum at the",
            "optionA": "  Indian Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Red Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Baltic Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Red Sea, one of the most saline bodies of water in the world, is an inlet of the Indian Ocean between Africa and Asia. The salinity of the Red Sea is greater than the world average, by approximately 5%. ",
            "keyString": "205523s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not the part of North Atlantic ocean current system?",
            "optionA": "  Irminger current ",
            "optionB": "  Labrador current ",
            "optionC": "  Brazilian current ",
            "optionD": "  Canarie current ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrazilian current is not the part of North Atlantic ocean current system. Brazil Current, branch of the Atlantic South Equatorial Current, flowing southward in the South Atlantic Ocean along the eastern coast of South America from Cape St. Roque, Brazil, to about latitude 30\u00b0\u201340\u00b0 S, where the northward-flowing Falkland Current deflects it to the east. ",
            "keyString": "205703s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an important condition for growth of coral?",
            "optionA": "  Wave-free salt water ",
            "optionB": "  Clean salt water ",
            "optionC": "  Warm seas ",
            "optionD": "  Plenty of sunlight ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWave-free salt water is not an important condition for growth of coral. Corals need saltwater to survive and require a certain balance in the ratio of salt to water. This is why corals don't live in areas where rivers drain fresh water into the ocean (\u201cestuaries\u201d). ",
            "keyString": "205871s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is called 'Herring Pond'?",
            "optionA": "  Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Black Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Dead Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Pacific Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe eastern coast of North America i.e. the Atlantic ocean is the habitat of Herring fish in abundance. That's why it is called herring pond. ",
            "keyString": "255975s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest lake in Africa is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lake Victoria ",
            "optionB": "  Lake Malawi ",
            "optionC": "  Lake Tanganyika ",
            "optionD": "  Lake Chad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLake Victoria, also called Victoria Nyanza, largest lake in Africa and chief reservoir of the Nile, lying mainly in Tanzania and Uganda but bordering on Kenya. Its area is 26,828 square miles (69,484 square km). ",
            "keyString": "256198s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If you travel along the Suez Canal from Port Said to Suez, you will come across several lakes. Which of the following lakes is not on this Canal?",
            "optionA": "  Great Bitter Lake ",
            "optionB": "  Little Bitter Lake ",
            "optionC": "  Lake Gatun ",
            "optionD": "  Lake Timsah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLake Gatun is not on Suez Canal. Gatun Lake, long artificial lake in Panama, constituting part of the Panama Canal system; its area is 166 square miles (430 square km). ",
            "keyString": "256386s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A broad, low embankment built up along the banks of a river channel during floods is called",
            "optionA": "  Delta ",
            "optionB": "  Levee ",
            "optionC": "  Flood Plain ",
            "optionD": "  Dune ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring floods the material carried by river is deposited at its banks forming a ridge like structure termed as natural levees. Levee, any low ridge or earthen embankment built along the edges of a stream or river channel to prevent flooding of the adjacent land.",
            "keyString": "256561s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are true of the Pacific Ocean?\nI. It is the largest of all water bodies\nII. It is roughly triangular in shape\nIII. The average depth is about 7300 m\nIV. Nearly 20,000 islands dot this vast ocean",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I and III ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following that are true of the Pacific Ocean are that it is the largest of all water bodies, it is roughly triangular in shape, the average depth is about 7300 m and nearly 20,000 islands dot this vast ocean. ",
            "keyString": "256755s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ideal conditions for coral growth are:\nI. water temperature around 20\u00b0C\nII. tropical waters (between 30\u00b0N and 30\u00b0S)\nIII. highly saline waterIV. adequate oxygen",
            "optionA": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionC": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionD": "  II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ideal conditions for coral growth are water temperature around 20\u00b0C, tropical waters (between 30\u00b0N and 30\u00b0S) and adequate oxygen. ",
            "keyString": "307698s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following current is responsible for rise in temperature in westen Europe?",
            "optionA": "  Labrador Current ",
            "optionB": "  Gulf stream ",
            "optionC": "  Canary Current ",
            "optionD": "  North Eqatorial ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe water currents are responsible to influence the climate of their nearby regions. Gulf Stream is warm water current, its extension North Atlantic Drift passes by European shore raising the temperature of the region.",
            "keyString": "307911s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct decreasing order of the share of different salts in sea water?",
            "optionA": "  Sodium chloride, magnesium chloride, magnesium sulphate, potassium sulphate ",
            "optionB": "  Sodium chloride, magnesium chloride, potassium sulphate, magnesium sulphate ",
            "optionC": "  Sodium chloride, magnesium sulphate, potassium sulphate, magnesium chloride ",
            "optionD": "  Sodium chloride, magnesium chloride, potassium sulphate, magnesium sulphate ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct decreasing order of the share of different salts in sea water are Sodium chloride, magnesium chloride, magnesium sulphate, potassium sulphate. ",
            "keyString": "308097s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following European countries borders Atlantic Ocean?",
            "optionA": "  Portugal ",
            "optionB": "  Austria ",
            "optionC": "  Finland ",
            "optionD": "  Romania ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEuropean countries Portugal borders Atlanic Ocean. The European (North East) Atlantic borders the five Member States of the UK, Ireland, France, Spain and Portugal, covering a vast area and a diverse range of ecosystems. More broadly, these ecosystems are split into the Celtic Seas, Bay of Biscay and Iberian Coast. ",
            "keyString": "308289s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Lena river passes through which country?",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  USA ",
            "optionC": "  Russia ",
            "optionD": "  Brazil ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLena river is a major river of Russia. It is a 440 km long river which originates from Lake Baikal and flows into the Arctic Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "308486s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The Benguela current had its influence in the formation of Kalahari Desert.\n2. The Agulhas current has its influence in the formation of Thar Desert.\n3. The currents of Northern Indian Ocean change their course of flow twice a year.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Benguela current had its influence in the formation of Kalahari Desert. The Benguela Current draws icy-cold waters from the Southern Ocean and carries them northward along the coast of Africa. Because of these cold waters, rain clouds do not develop over the southwest coast of Africa, contributing to the parched climate of the Kalahari and Namib deserts. The currents of Northern Indian Ocean change their course of flow twice a year. The currents in the northern Indian Ocean change their flow direction twice a year due to north-east and south-west monsoon winds.",
            "keyString": "350863s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On the bank of which river is New York situated?",
            "optionA": "  River Colorado ",
            "optionB": "  River Hudson ",
            "optionC": "  River Mississippi ",
            "optionD": "  River Amazon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the bank of Hudson River, New York is situated. The Hudson River is a 315-mile (507 km) river that flows from north to south primarily through eastern New York in the United States. ",
            "keyString": "351386s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Water exists in how much part of the world?",
            "optionA": "  0.7 ",
            "optionB": "  0.8 ",
            "optionC": "  0.25 ",
            "optionD": "  0.55 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuch of the earth surface is covered by water making it the Blue planet. About 2/3 of earth surface comprises of water of water i.e. equivalent to 70%. ",
            "keyString": "351588s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest freshwater lake in the world ?",
            "optionA": "  Lake Tanganyika ",
            "optionB": "  Lake Superior ",
            "optionC": "  Lake Baikal ",
            "optionD": "  Lake Michigan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth America's Lake Superior is the largest freshwater lake in the world. ",
            "keyString": "351708s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements are true regarding distribution of world population?\nI. Only 10% of the total population lives in the southern hemisphere\nII. Nearly two-thirds of the total population live within 500 km of sea\nIII. Nearly 80% of the total population lives within 500 meters altitude above sea levels",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the following statements are true regarding distribution of world population. Only 10% of the total population lives in the southern hemisphere, nearly two-thirds of the total population live within 500 km of sea and nearly 80% of the total population lives within 500 meters altitude above sea level. ",
            "keyString": "351811s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a landform which results due to rejuvenation of a river?",
            "optionA": "  Incised meander ",
            "optionB": "  Knick point ",
            "optionC": "  Oxbow lake ",
            "optionD": "  Rive terrace ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxbow lake is not a landform which results due to rejuvenation of a river. River rejuvenation involves a renewed period of vertical erosion to achieve a new and lower base level. An oxbow is a crescent-shaped lake lying alongside a winding river. ",
            "keyString": "400240s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which river is \"Grand canyon\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mississippi ",
            "optionB": "  Colorado ",
            "optionC": "  Columbia ",
            "optionD": "  Ohara ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA steep sided canyon is formed by the river Colorado in the State of Arizona in U.S.A. The Colorado River in the Grand Canyon faces a battery of threats, each with a critical decision point. ",
            "keyString": "400288s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A ship met with an accident at 30\u00baC and 35\u00baN. The ship was sailing in the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Baltic Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Black Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Red Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA ship met with an accident at 30\u00baC and 35\u00baN. The ship was sailing in the Mediterranean Sea. The latitude of Mediterranean Sea is 34.553127, and the longitude is 18.048012. Mediterranean Sea is located at Italy country in the Seas place category with the gps coordinates of 34\u00b0 33' 11.2572'' N and 18\u00b0 2' 52.8432'' E. ",
            "keyString": "400436s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The tides in the Sea are primarily due to",
            "optionA": "  The atmospheric effect of the Earth ",
            "optionB": "  The gravitational effect of Venus on the Earth ",
            "optionC": "   The gravitational effect of the Sun on the\nEarth ",
            "optionD": "  The gravitational effect of the Moon on the\nEarth ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rise & fall of sea water due to gravity is termed as tide. It is combined effect of gravitational forces ofmoon and sun. As moon is closer to Earth than Sun, its gravitational pull is more as compared to that of Sun. ",
            "keyString": "400552s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When water freezes in the polar seas the salts ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Form a layer on top ",
            "optionB": "  Remain in the subsurface water that does not freeze ",
            "optionC": "  Sink to the bottom ",
            "optionD": "  Partly freeze and partly sink to the bottom ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen water freezes in the polar seas the salts remain in the subsurface water that does not freeze. Seawater of typical saltiness freezes at about -1.8 \u00b0C. The water in contact with the freezing ice is cold and contains some of the salt excluded from the ice, so it is more dense than the warmer water below, and it sinks, mixing with the deeper water. This mixture ends up on the bottom of the ocean. ",
            "keyString": "400662s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following percentages regarding the world's water resources:\n1. Oceans and lakes - 95%\n2. Frozen as ice - 4%\n3. For man's use - 1%\nWhich of the above are correct percentages?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the three are correct percentages. Oceans and lakes - 95%, Frozen as ice - 4%, For man's use - 1%. ",
            "keyString": "457856s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the deepest lake?",
            "optionA": "  Lake Victoria ",
            "optionB": "  Caspian Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Lake Superior ",
            "optionD": "  Lake Baikal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLake Baikal in southern Russia is the world's deepest lake. It is an estimated 5,387 feet deep (1,642 meters), and its bottom is approximately 3,893 feet (1,187 meters) below sea level. Lake Baikal is also the world's largest freshwater lake in terms of volume. ",
            "keyString": "511137s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The smallest amongst the following islands is ________.",
            "optionA": "  Borneo ",
            "optionB": "  Greenland ",
            "optionC": "  Sumatra ",
            "optionD": "  New Guinea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe smallest amongst the following islands is Sumatra. Sumatra, a large Indonesian island west of Java and south of the Malay Peninsula, is known for its rugged tropical terrain, wildlife and smoldering volcanoes. ",
            "keyString": "511261s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An ox-bow lake is a ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lake formed behind an off-shore bar ",
            "optionB": "  Lake occupying a volcanic crater ",
            "optionC": "  Lake formed due to cut off meander ",
            "optionD": "  Lake occupying a hollow scooped by a glacier ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn oxbow lake is a special kind of lake that only forms next to meandering rivers. It is shaped like a crescent or a horseshoe and presents a unique ecosystem separate from the river. ",
            "keyString": "511585s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the rivers flow into the landlocked Caspian Sea?\n1. Don\n2. Syr Darya\n3. Volga\n4. Ural",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVolga and Ural rivers flow into the landlocked Caspian Sea. The Volga River (about 80% of the inflow) and the Ural River discharge into the Caspian Sea, but it is endorheic, i.e. there is no natural outflow (other than by evaporation). ",
            "keyString": "511862s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sea is landlocked?",
            "optionA": "  Red Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Timor Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Northern Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Aral Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe incredible, shrinking Aral Sea is a landlocked sea--really a lake--in Central Asia, lying between between Kazakhstan and Uzbekistan in the middle of a semi-arid and desert region. ",
            "keyString": "603885s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Erosion of soil by a river mainly depends upon ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Its depth ",
            "optionB": "  Its length ",
            "optionC": "  Its speed at which it flows ",
            "optionD": "  Its width ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFlowing water can erode rocks and soil. Erosion of soil by a river mainly depends upon Its speed at which it flows. ",
            "keyString": "605328s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Canals in Western Europe are mainly used for ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Irrigation ",
            "optionB": "  Inland navigation ",
            "optionC": "  Ship building ",
            "optionD": "  Trade ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Canals in Western Europe are mainly used for Inland navigation. ",
            "keyString": "605484s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A drainage pattern where a river is joined by its tributaries approximately at right angles is",
            "optionA": "  Dendritic ",
            "optionB": "  Trellis ",
            "optionC": "  Rectangular ",
            "optionD": "  Radial ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA drainage pattern where a river is joined by its tributaries approximately at right angles is called \" Trellis\". When a river is joined by its tributaries at almost right angles, it develops a trellis pattern. Trellis pattern develops where hard and soft rocks exist parallel to each other. ",
            "keyString": "606093s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mongla port is located in",
            "optionA": "  Srilanka ",
            "optionB": "  Bangladesh ",
            "optionC": "  Bhutan ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMongla Port is the second busiest seaport of Bangladesh. It is located in Bagerhat District in the southwestern part of the country; and lies 62 kilometres north of the Bay of Bengal coastline. ",
            "keyString": "606156s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river crosses Tropic of Capricorn twice?",
            "optionA": "  Vaal River ",
            "optionB": "  Limpopo River ",
            "optionC": "  Niger River ",
            "optionD": "  Zambezi River ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLimpopo flows through Mozambique. After Zambezi,it is 2nd largest African river to fall in the Indian Ocean. The Limpopo River in Africa crosses the Tropic of Capricorn twice.The Tropic of Capricorn is located south of the Equator. ",
            "keyString": "654977s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which if the following river crosses the Equator twice.",
            "optionA": "  Congo ",
            "optionB": "  Amazon ",
            "optionC": "  Niger ",
            "optionD": "  Nile ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCongo is the 2nd largest river of Africa after Nile. It is also the World's deepest river with depth of upto 220m at some places. It flows through Zaire, hence called river Zairn. The Congo River crosses the equator twice, once in each direction.",
            "keyString": "655011s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which river crosses the Equator twice?",
            "optionA": "  Amazon ",
            "optionB": "  Congo ",
            "optionC": "  Nile ",
            "optionD": "  Orinoco ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCongo is the 2nd largest river of Africa after Nile. It is also the World's deepest river with depth of upto 220m at some places. It flows through Zaire, hence called river Zairn. The Congo River crosses the equator twice, once in each direction. ",
            "keyString": "655028s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Coral reefs are formed by ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Volcanic rocks ",
            "optionB": "  Marine sediments ",
            "optionC": "  Chlorine material precipitated from sea water ",
            "optionD": "  Tiny colonial marine animals which construct limestone skeleton material ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoral reefs are formed by tiny colonial marine animals which construct limestone skeleton material. Massive reef structures are formed when each individual stony coral organism or polyp secretes a skeleton of calcium carbonate. ",
            "keyString": "655041s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following separates Asia and North America?",
            "optionA": "  Bass Strait ",
            "optionB": "  Dover Strait ",
            "optionC": "  Bering Strait ",
            "optionD": "  Cook Strait ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBering Strait lies between Eastern Russia & Alaska (U.S.A). Bering Strait, Russian Proliv Beringa, strait linking the Arctic Ocean with the Bering Sea and separating the continents of Asia and North America at their closest point. The strait averages 98 to 164 feet (30 to 50 metres) in depth and at its narrowest is about 53 miles (85 km) wide.",
            "keyString": "655054s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following best explain why the lower course of a river is sometimes choked with sediments?\n1. The valley of a river is widest in its lower course.\n2. The velocity of a river in its lower course is low.\n3. The delta sometimes develops in a river's lower course.\n4. Much of the river water is drawn for irrigation in the lower course.",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 3 and 4 only ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 4 only ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe lower course of a river is sometimes choked with sediments because the valley of a river is widest in its lower course, the velocity of a river in its lower course is low and the delta sometimes develops in a river's lower course. ",
            "keyString": "702107s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best way of conservation of water resources is",
            "optionA": "  Storage of rain water ",
            "optionB": "  Sustainable water consumption ",
            "optionC": "  Encouraging reformation of natural plants ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the above given points are worthy so as to conserve water. As rain water is the pure water, it can be stored & utilized as per the needs. Hence underground water tanks in Rajasthan, overhead tanks in Tamil Nadu are compulsory. Over utilisation such as over irrigation depletes water resources, hence should be controlled & water be used wisely. Natural water bodies be replenished through reformation. ",
            "keyString": "702144s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Farakka barrage is a major reason for contention between India and ________.",
            "optionA": "  Bangladesh  ",
            "optionB": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionC": "  China ",
            "optionD": "  Nepal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFarakka barrage is a major reason for contention between India and Bangladesh. The Farakka Barrage was created by India in 1975 to divert water from Ganges river system but this has resulted in a reduced flow towards Bangladesh which is a lower riparia state to this system. ",
            "keyString": "702159s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Suez Canal joins ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Red Sea and Arabian Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Red Sea and Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Arabian Sea and Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionD": "  North Sea and Baltic Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSuez Canal is an artificial sea-level waterway in Egypt. It links the Mediterranean with the Red Sea through Isthmus of Suez. It was first opened in 1869 after a decade of construction. Strategically and economically it is one of the most important waterways in the world providing the shortest sea link between Asia and Europe. ",
            "keyString": "702172s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river stages and features is/are wrongly matched?\n1. Mountain stage : waterfalls\n2. Plain stage : oxbow lake\n3. Plain stage : delta\n4. Mountain stage : deposition",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Plain stage : delta and Mountain stage : deposition are wrongly matched.",
            "keyString": "702183s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ocean surface currents follow clockwise circulatory paths in the northern parts of the Pacific and Atlantic oceans due to the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Convergence and divergence movements ",
            "optionB": "  Coriolis force ",
            "optionC": "  Density differences in seawater ",
            "optionD": "  Impact of prevailing winds ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ocean surface currents follow clockwise circulatory paths in the northern parts of the Pacific and Atlantic oceans due to the Corioli's force. The Coriolis effect shifts surface currents by angles of about 45\u00b0. In the Northern Hemisphere, ocean currents are deflected to the right, in a clockwise motion. ",
            "keyString": "739703s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why are the ports of Baltic sea opened for trade in winter?",
            "optionA": "  It is tropical belt ",
            "optionB": "  North Atlantic warm currents flow in this region ",
            "optionC": "  Local factors keep it warm ",
            "optionD": "  Western disturbances increase the temperature ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth Atlantic warm currents flow in this region the ports of Baltic sea opened for trade in winter. Extended Gulf stream current above 40N latitude in Atlantic is termed as North Atlantic Drift, a warm water current, flowing from tropics towards pole affecting climate of near by coastal regions. Hence, sea ports in West Europe between 50N - 60N Latitude remain open in winters also. ",
            "keyString": "739741s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The reason behind broadening the river valley is",
            "optionA": "  Corrosion ",
            "optionB": "  Soil Erosion ",
            "optionC": "  Attrition ",
            "optionD": "  Hydraulic Action ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe reason behind broadening the river valley is soil erosion. As the river water comes in contact with soil and rocks on its banks, it weathers up the material & after sometime this weathered up material is eroded away by same river water. Hence river valley is broadened. ",
            "keyString": "739761s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following factors is responsible for the change in the regular direction of the ocean currents in the Indian Ocean?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Ocean is 'half an ocean' ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Ocean has Monsoon drift ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Ocean is a land-locked ocean ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Ocean has greater variation in salinity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Ocean has Monsoon drift factors is responsible for the change in the regular direction of the ocean currents in the Indian Ocean. The currents in the northern portion of the Indian Ocean change their direction from season to season in response to the seasonal rhythm of the monsoons. ",
            "keyString": "739782s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Imaginary lines connecting places in oceans having equal salinity are called",
            "optionA": "  Isotherms ",
            "optionB": "  Isobars ",
            "optionC": "  Isohalines ",
            "optionD": "  Isohyets ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tisohaline is a line or surface drawn on a map or chart to indicate connecting points of equal salinity in the ocean. ",
            "keyString": "739797s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the correct order of ocean currents in the northern part of Pacific ocean in clockwise direction?",
            "optionA": "  North equatorial - California Kuroshio - North equatorial ",
            "optionB": "  North equatorial \u2013 California \u2013 Kuroshio - Pacific drift-North equatorial ",
            "optionC": "  North equatorial - Kuroshio - Pacific drift - North equatorial ",
            "optionD": "  North equatorial - Pacific drift \u2013 Kuroshio \u2013 California - North equatorial ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct order of ocean currents in the northern part of Pacific ocean in clockwise direction is North equatorial - Kuroshio - Pacific drift - North equatorial. ",
            "keyString": "782557s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers flowing through Pakistan has its source of origin in that country itself?",
            "optionA": "  Ravi ",
            "optionB": "  Jhelum ",
            "optionC": "  Chenab ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSutlej flows through the historic crossroad region of Punjab in northern India and Pakistan. It is located north of the Vindhya Range, south of the Hindu Kush segment of the Himalayas, and east of the Central Sulaiman Range in Pakistan.",
            "keyString": "782591s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the factors that are mainly responsible for the movements of surface oceanic currents?\n1. Prevailing winds\n2. Earth's Rotation\n3. Earthquake activity\n4. Bottom Topography\n5. Difference in the density of seawater",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 2 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 and 5 ",
            "optionD": "  3, 4 and 5 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe factors that are mainly responsible for the movements of surface oceanic currents are Prevailing winds, Earth's Rotation and Difference in the density of seawater. ",
            "keyString": "782608s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What percentage of World's fresh water is stored in the form of glacier ice",
            "optionA": "  0.5 ",
            "optionB": "  0.1 ",
            "optionC": "  1.7 ",
            "optionD": "  0.3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe amount of water locked up in ice and snow is only about 1.7% of all water on Earth, but the majority of total freshwater on Earth, about 68.7%, is held in ice caps and glaciers. ",
            "keyString": "782631s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sea water is saltier than rain water because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Sea animals are salt producing ",
            "optionB": "  The air around the sea is saltish ",
            "optionC": "  River wash away salts from earth and pour them into the sea ",
            "optionD": "  Sea beds have salt producing mines ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSea water is saltier than rain water because river wash away salts from earth and pour them into the sea. Rain water is mostly pure water. Sea water has salt (and other minerals) dissolved in it. Water evaporates from the sea to form clouds (which eventually cause rain) - but the salt is left behind in the ocean. Thus, you can't have salt-water rain. ",
            "keyString": "782645s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest waterfall of the world is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Niagara Falls ",
            "optionB": "  Boyoma Falls ",
            "optionC": "  Salto Angel Falls ",
            "optionD": "  Khone Falls ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAngel Falls (Salto \u00c1ngel) in Venezuela is the highest waterfall in the world. The falls are 3230 feet in height, with an uninterrupted drop of 2647 feet. Angel Falls is located on a tributary of the Rio Caroni. ",
            "keyString": "818037s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A stretch of sea water, partly or fully separated by a narrow strip from the main sea is called",
            "optionA": "  Bay ",
            "optionB": "  Isthmus ",
            "optionC": "  Lagoon ",
            "optionD": "  Strait ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA stretch of sea water, partly or fully separated by a narrow strip from the main sea is called Lagoon. Lagoon is a relief feature in which shallow water body is separated from larger water body by barrier island or reef. ",
            "keyString": "818073s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The World's longest river is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Nile ",
            "optionB": "  Ganges ",
            "optionC": "  Amazon ",
            "optionD": "  Mississippi \u2013 Missouri ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nile is credited as the longest river in the world. Its main source is Lake Victoria in east central Africa. From its farthest stream in Burundi, it extends 6,695 km (4,160 miles) in length. ",
            "keyString": "818090s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The longest river of Europe is",
            "optionA": "  Rhine ",
            "optionB": "  Rhone ",
            "optionC": "  Danube ",
            "optionD": "  Volga ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Volga River is the longest river in Europe. Its basin lies entirely within the Russian federation. It is often called Mother Volga by the Russians. ",
            "keyString": "818104s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs of ocean currents meet each other near Newfound land?",
            "optionA": "  Canaries and Labrador ",
            "optionB": "  Gulf stream and Labrador ",
            "optionC": "  Gulfstream and Canaries ",
            "optionD": "  Kuroshio and Kurile ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGulf stream and Labrador of ocean currents meet each other near Newfound land. The Gulf Stream reaches Cape Hatteras, North Carolina, the cold Labrador Current that flows from the north separates it from the coast. ",
            "keyString": "818117s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest irrigation canal in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Panama Canal ",
            "optionB": "  Sirhind Canal ",
            "optionC": "  Suez Canal ",
            "optionD": "  Indira Gandhi Canal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indira Gandhi Canal is the longest canal in India and the largest irrigation project in the world. Indira Gandhi Canal is 649 km long and consists of Rajasthan feeder canal and Rajasthan main canal and runs through 167 km in Punjab and Haryana and remaining 492 km in Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "860651s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Strait connecting Arabian Sea and the Bay of Bengal is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Bering Strait ",
            "optionB": "  Dover Strait ",
            "optionC": "  Palk Strait ",
            "optionD": "  Vermosa Strait ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Strait connecting Arabian Sea and the Bay of Bengal is Palk Strait. It connects the Bay of Bengal in the northeast with Palk Bay in the southwest. The strait is 53 to 82 kilometres (33 to 51 mi) wide. ",
            "keyString": "860702s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are the Balearic Islands located?",
            "optionA": "  Mediterranean Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Black Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Baltic Sea ",
            "optionD": "  North Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Balearic Islands is a Spanish archipelago located in the Mediterranean Sea. It is an autonomous community of Spain. It has four major islands and several minor ones.",
            "keyString": "860721s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following countries does not border Mediterranean Sea?",
            "optionA": "  Malta ",
            "optionB": "  Libya ",
            "optionC": "  Italy ",
            "optionD": "  Bulgaria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBulgaria does not border mediterranean sea, shares the boundary with Black-sea. ",
            "keyString": "860736s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are factors that effect the movement of ocean currents?\nI. Earth's gravity\nII. Atmospheric pressure\nIII. Winds\nIV. Salinity of the water\nV. Seasonal Variations",
            "optionA": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and V ",
            "optionC": "  III, IV and V ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe factors that effect the movement of ocean currents are Earth's gravity, Atmospheric pressure, Winds, Salinity of the water and Seasonal Variations. ",
            "keyString": "860750s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ocean currents transfer heat from ________ ",
            "optionA": "  One sea or ocean to another ",
            "optionB": "  One coast to another ",
            "optionC": "  The surface of the sea to greater depths ",
            "optionD": "  Lower to higher latitudes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ocean currents and winds transport the heat from the lower latitudes near the equator to higher latitudes near the poles. The transfer of heat energy within the atmosphere, hydrosphere, and the Earth's surface and interior occurs as a result of radiation, convection, and conduction. Ocean currents play a significant role in transferring this heat toward the poles. ",
            "keyString": "899897s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mr. X has been invited to participate in a conference to be held at Buenos Aires. He has chosen the following shortest flight route: Mumbai to Frankfurt (non-stop) Frankfurt to Sao Paulo (non-stop) Sao Paulo to Buenos Aires (non-stop). Which one of the following seas will likely to be flown over by Mr. X?",
            "optionA": "  Tasman Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Labrador Sea ",
            "optionC": "  Beaufort Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Black Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlack Sea will likely to be flown over by Mr. X. ",
            "keyString": "899931s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Tsunami\" is the name given to which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Earthquake ",
            "optionB": "  Cyclone ",
            "optionC": "  Tidal Waves ",
            "optionD": "  Undersea Waves ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTsunami is a Japanese word meaning harbour wave. Although both are sea waves, a tsunami and a tidal wave are two different and unrelated phenomena. A tidal wave is a shallow water wave caused by the gravitational interactions between the Sun, Moon, and Earth. (\"Tidal wave\" was used in earlier times to describe what we now call a tsunami.) ",
            "keyString": "899947s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main area of production of icebergs is found in .",
            "optionA": "  The West Coast of Greenland ",
            "optionB": "  The East Coast of Japan ",
            "optionC": "  The North Coast of Siberia ",
            "optionD": "  The West Coast of Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principal origin of those icebergs that reach the North Atlantic Ocean are the 100 or so major tidewater glaciers of West Coast Greenland. ",
            "keyString": "899960s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The following statements are made about ocean currents:1. They are warm off the west coast of continents within the tropics2. They move clockwise in the oceans of the Southern Hemisphere3. They move clockwise in the oceans of the Northern HemisphereWhich of the above are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOcean currents are warm off the west coast of continents within the tropics. They move clockwise in the oceans of the Northern Hemisphere. ",
            "keyString": "899973s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The current produced by upwelling of cold water off the coast of Chile and Peru is known as",
            "optionA": "  El Nino ",
            "optionB": "  Humboldt current ",
            "optionC": "  Agulhas current ",
            "optionD": "  Canary current ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeru Current, also called Humboldt Current, cold-water current of the southeast Pacific Ocean, with a width of about 900 km (550 mi). The cold flow is intensified by upwelling of deep water caused by the combined effects of the drag of surface winds of the Southeast Trades and the Earth\u2019s rotation.",
            "keyString": "939692s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The important fishing areas called Grand Bank and Georges Bank located in the waters of which one of the following?",
            "optionA": "  North Pacific ",
            "optionB": "  South Pacific ",
            "optionC": "  South-west Atlantic ",
            "optionD": "  North-west Atlantic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are five major fishing grounds of world. It includes Grand Bank and the Georges Bank area of the Northwest Atlantic. ",
            "keyString": "939728s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following countries is planning to construct a rival to the Panama Canal to link the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans?",
            "optionA": "  Colombia ",
            "optionB": "  Costa Rica ",
            "optionC": "  Guatemala ",
            "optionD": "  Nicaragua ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNicaragua, the poorest country in mainland South America, announced that it will break ground on a new canal linking the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. ",
            "keyString": "939744s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An artificial navigation channel is called",
            "optionA": "  Canal ",
            "optionB": "  Greenhouse effect ",
            "optionC": "  Flord ",
            "optionD": "  Caprock ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCanals are artificial waterways constructed for irrigation, drainage, river overflows, water supplies, communications, and navigation, or in connection with power generation from hydroelectric dams. Indira Gandhi Canal is the largest canal in India.",
            "keyString": "939759s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the biggest Gulf of the World?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf of Mexico ",
            "optionB": "  Gulf of Persia ",
            "optionC": "   Bay of Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Hudson bay ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gulf of Mexico, bordered by the United States, Mexico, and the island nation of Cuba, is the worlds largest gulf. It has a coastline of about 5,000 kilometers (3,100 miles). The Gulf of Mexico is connected to the Atlantic Ocean by the Straits of Florida, between Cuba and the U.S. state of Florida. ",
            "keyString": "939772s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The direction of ocean currents is reversed with season ________ ",
            "optionA": "  In the Pacific Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  In the Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  In the Indian Ocean ",
            "optionD": "  In the Mediterranean Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe north-easterly direction of winter monsoon winds becomes south-westerly during summer season in the northern hemisphere. This reversal of direction of monsoon winds also reverses the direction of ocean currents of Indian Ocean during summer season. ",
            "keyString": "977210s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tokyo, the capital of Japan is situated in the island of",
            "optionA": "  Hokkaido ",
            "optionB": "  Honshu ",
            "optionC": "  Shikoku ",
            "optionD": "  Kyushu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTokyo, the capital of Japan is situated in the island of Honshu. Tokyo forms part of the Kanto region on the southeastern side of Japan's main island, Honshu, and includes the Izu Islands and Ogasawara Islands. ",
            "keyString": "977244s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest island of the Philippines?",
            "optionA": "  Mindanao ",
            "optionB": "  Palawan ",
            "optionC": "  Luzon ",
            "optionD": "  Negnos ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe biggest islands of the Philippines is Luzon. Luzon ranks as the Philippine's most populous and largest island. ",
            "keyString": "977260s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ islands are the \"cross roads of the Pacific\".",
            "optionA": "  Fiji ",
            "optionB": "  Falkland ",
            "optionC": "  Windward ",
            "optionD": "  Hawaiian ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHawaiian islands are the \"cross roads of the Pacific\". Air travel transformed Hawaii. It made the islands' geographic isolation irrelevant and tourism the foundation of the state's economy. ",
            "keyString": "977272s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following countries does not border the Caspian sea?",
            "optionA": "  Armenia ",
            "optionB": "  Azerbaijan ",
            "optionC": "  Kazakhstan ",
            "optionD": "  Turkmenistan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArmenia does not border the Caspian sea. Armenia is a landlocked country in the Transcaucasia region, between the Black and Caspian Seas, bordered on the north and east by Georgia and Azerbaijan and on the south and west by Iran and Turkey. ",
            "keyString": "977284s29m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Grand Banks are famous fishing grounds in the ________ region.",
            "optionA": "  North-West Pacific ",
            "optionB": "  South-East Pacific ",
            "optionC": "  North-West Atlantic ",
            "optionD": "  North-East Atlantic ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGrand Banks, portion of the North American continental shelf in the Atlantic Ocean, lying southeast of Newfoundland island, Canada. It as an international fishing ground, the banks extend for 350 miles (560 km) north to south and for 420 miles (675 km) east to west. ",
            "keyString": "13204s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following seas is without a coastline?",
            "optionA": "  White sea ",
            "optionB": "  Sargasso sea ",
            "optionC": "  Sea of Okhotsk ",
            "optionD": "  Tasman sea ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sargasso Sea, located entirely within the Atlantic Ocean, is the only sea without a land boundary. Mats of free-floating sargassum, a common seaweed found in the Sargasso Sea, provide shelter and habitat to many animals. ",
            "keyString": "13276s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under normal conditions, which one of the following is the correct sequential developments of features made by fluvial action?",
            "optionA": "  Waterfalls - Meander bars - River terraces - Oxbow lakes ",
            "optionB": "  Meander bars - River terraces \u2013 Waterfalls - Oxbow lakes ",
            "optionC": "  Waterfalls - River terraces \u2013 Meander bars - Oxbow lakes ",
            "optionD": "  River terraces - Meander \u2013 Waterfalls - Oxbow lakes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder normal conditions, the correct sequential developments of features made by fluvial action are Waterfalls - River terraces \u2013 Meander bars - Oxbow lakes. ",
            "keyString": "13308s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maximum amount of herring fish is obtained from ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The North Sea around the Netherlands ",
            "optionB": "  The coastal areas from Alaska to California ",
            "optionC": "  The Sea of Japan ",
            "optionD": "  The Gulf of Mexico ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaximum amount of herring fish is obtained from The North Sea around the Netherlands. The North Sea has long been the site of important European shipping lanes as well as a major fishery. ",
            "keyString": "13339s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest reserves of fresh water on the Earth's surface is in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  North America ",
            "optionB": "  South America ",
            "optionC": "  Russia ",
            "optionD": "  Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest reserves of fresh water on the Earth's surface is in North America. The American Great Lakes account for 21% of the Earth's surface fresh water. ",
            "keyString": "13358s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Bermuda situated in Western Atlantic Ocean is a United Kingdom Overseas Territory.\n2. 38th Parallel divided boundary between North and South Vietnam before unification\n3. Bahamas situated near Florida is one of the states of USA.\nWhich of these statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBermuda situated in Western Atlantic Ocean is a United Kingdom Overseas Territory.Bermuda, self-governing British overseas territory in the western North Atlantic Ocean. It is an archipelago of 7 main islands and about 170 additional (named) islets and rocks, situated about 650 miles (1,050 km) east of Cape Hatteras (North Carolina, U.S.).",
            "keyString": "53462s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Falkland Islands are situated in Pacific Ocean\n2. Red Sea separates Sudan from Egypt.\n3. England, Norway, Denmark surround North Sea.\nWhich of these statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  2 only ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  3 only ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEngland, Norway, Denmark surround North Sea. The North Sea - a part of the Atlantic Ocean - is bordered by Norway and Denmark, Scotland and England, (and in the southeast)by the Frisian Islands and Germany, the Netherlands, Belgium and France. ",
            "keyString": "53501s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Greenland is an overseas territory of France.\n2. Bermuda, an overseas territory of UK, is situated in Western Atlantic.\n3. State of Bahrain is situated in the Persian Gulf.\nWhich of these statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBerumuda, an overseas territory of UK, is situated in Western Atlantic. Bermuda, self-governing British overseas territory in the western North Atlantic Ocean. It is an archipelago of 7 main islands and about 170 additional (named) islets and rocks, situated about 650 miles (1,050 km) east of Cape Hatteras (North Carolina, U.S.). State of Bahrain is situated in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain, small Arab state situated in a bay on the southwestern coast of the Persian Gulf. It is an archipelago consisting of Bahrain Island and some 30 smaller islands. Its name is from the Arabic term al-bahrayn, meaning \u201ctwo seas.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "53519s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest coral reef in the world is found near the coast of which one of the following countries ?",
            "optionA": "  Australia ",
            "optionB": "  Cuba ",
            "optionC": "  Ghana ",
            "optionD": "  Philippines ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest coral reef in the world is found near the coast of Australia. The Great Barrier Reef is the world's largest coral reef system composed of over 2,900 individual reefs and 900 islands stretching for over 2,300 kilometres (1,400 mi) over an area of approximately 344,400 square kilometres (133,000 sq mi). The reef is located in the Coral Sea, off the coast of Queensland, Australia. ",
            "keyString": "53537s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The full name of OTEC",
            "optionA": "  Offshore Thermal Energy Conservation ",
            "optionB": "  Ocean Terminal Energy Conservation ",
            "optionC": "  Oil and Thermal Energy Conservation ",
            "optionD": "  Ocean Thermal Energy Conservation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe full name of OTEC is Ocean Thermal Energy Conservation. Ocean thermal energy conversion (OTEC) is a process or technology for producing energy by harnessing the temperature differences (thermal gradients) between ocean surface waters and deep ocean waters. ",
            "keyString": "53550s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which of the following, Grand Bank and Dogger Bank are related?",
            "optionA": "  Tidal power plants ",
            "optionB": "  Main fish catching zone ",
            "optionC": "  Scuba diving ",
            "optionD": "  Shipping ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThese are the shallow sea zones where cold and warm water currents mix well making them great breedinggrounds for fishes. At Grand Bank cold Labrador and warm Gulf Stream meets. Dogger Bank in North Sea is shallow sea water zone which receives ample sunlight preparing grounds depression on earth. Both are main fish catching zone. ",
            "keyString": "138059s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the longest current known as \"Black Current\" due to its black colour?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf Stream ",
            "optionB": "  Kuroshio ",
            "optionC": "  California Current ",
            "optionD": "  Antarctica Current ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kuroshio, one of the three largest of the world\u2019s ocean currents, has long fascinated humans. The Japanese named it Kuroshio, or black current, for its dark, cobalt blue waters. Physical oceanographer Steven Jayne said, \u201cThe Kuroshio is the strongest current in the Pacific Ocean, and is also one of the most intense air-sea heat exchange regions on the globe. It influences climate as far as North America.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "138092s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rivers in \"Annular\" pattern flow in which direction?",
            "optionA": "  West to East ",
            "optionB": "  North to South ",
            "optionC": "  Like a ring ",
            "optionD": "  Transverse direction ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRivers in \"Annular\" pattern flow in like a ring. In this pattern streams take roughly circular or concentric path along weak rock belt resembling ring like pattern. Example - The Amarkantak Plateau. ",
            "keyString": "138110s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following features is not formed by running water?",
            "optionA": "  Valleys ",
            "optionB": "  Tunnels ",
            "optionC": "  Gorges ",
            "optionD": "  Canyons ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTunnels is not formed by running water. A tunnel is an underground passageway, dug through the surrounding soil/earth/rock and enclosed except for entrance and exit, commonly at each end. ",
            "keyString": "138124s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ocean current is not found in Atlantic ocean?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf Stream ",
            "optionB": "  Brazilian Stream ",
            "optionC": "  Peru Current ",
            "optionD": "  Canary Current ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeru Current also know as Humboldt Current is a cold water current in Pacific Ocean, the rest of the current are of Atlantic Ocean.",
            "keyString": "138136s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The biggest island at the tip of South America is the",
            "optionA": "  Falkland Island ",
            "optionB": "  Long Island ",
            "optionC": "  Tierra Del Fuego Island ",
            "optionD": "  Azores Island ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe biggest island at the tip of South America is the Tierra Del Fuego Island. Located at the southern tip of South America, the Tierra Del Fuego archipelago includes one large island (18,571 sq miles, 48,100 sq km) in size, and a series of smaller ones.",
            "keyString": "175956s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following group of people changes their house types according to seasons?",
            "optionA": "  Pygmies ",
            "optionB": "  Bantus ",
            "optionC": "  Kirghiz ",
            "optionD": "  Eskimos ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKirghiz group of people changes their house types according to seasons. ",
            "keyString": "175991s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the narrow strip which connects two water bodies or Sea or Ocean?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf ",
            "optionB": "  Strait ",
            "optionC": "   Peninsula ",
            "optionD": "  Isthmus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA strait lies between two land masses and connects two larger bodies of water, an isthmus lies between two bodies of water and connects two larger land masses. e.g. Palk Strait connects Gulf of Mannar & Bay of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "176007s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following features are formed by the river in its upper course?\n1. Gorge\n2. Canyon\n3. Meander",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGorge and Meander features are formed by the river in its upper course. ",
            "keyString": "176021s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Given below are names of four oceans smallest to the biggest in terms of area is:\n1. Atlantic\n2. Arctic\n3. Indian\n4. Pacific",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "optionB": "  4, 1, 3, 2 ",
            "optionC": "  3, 4, 1, 2 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 3, 1, 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFour oceans smallest to the biggest in terms of area are Arctic, Indian, Atlantic and Pacific. The Arctic Ocean occupies a roughly circular basin and covers an area of about 14,056,000 km2 (5,427,000 sq mi), almost the size of Antarctica. Indian Ocean, third largest ocean, c.28,350,000 sq mi (73,427,000 sq km). The Atlantic Ocean is the second largest of the world's oceans, with an area of about 106,460,000 square kilometers (41,100,000 square miles). The Pacific Ocean encompasses approximately one-third of the Earth's surface, having an area of 165,200,000 km2 (63,800,000 sq mi). ",
            "keyString": "176036s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fishing grounds are concentrated in the high latitudes. The reasons are:\n1. great length of indented coastline\n2. extensive continental shelves\n3. water temperatures lower than 20\u00b0C\n4. sparse population",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFishing grounds are concentrated in the high latitudes. The reasons are there great length of indented coastline, extensive continental shelves and water temperatures lower than 20\u00b0C. ",
            "keyString": "214556s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Kiel Canal links the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Mediterranean Sea and Black Sea ",
            "optionB": "  Pacific Ocean and Atlantic Ocean ",
            "optionC": "  North Sea and Baltic Sea ",
            "optionD": "  Mediterranean Sea and Red Sea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kiel Canal links the North Sea and Baltic Sea. The canal constitutes the safest, most convenient, shortest, and cheapest shipping route between the two seas. ",
            "keyString": "214594s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The deepest surface depression on earth is",
            "optionA": "  Kuri Trench ",
            "optionB": "  Mariana Trench ",
            "optionC": "  Tonga-Kermadec Trench ",
            "optionD": "  Bentley Subglacial Trench ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe deepest known depression on the earth is the Mariana Trench, which lies east of the Mariana Islands in the western North Pacific Ocean; it reaches 11,034 metres (36,200 feet) at its deepest point. ",
            "keyString": "214610s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Major source of oceanic salinity is",
            "optionA": "  Rivers ",
            "optionB": "  Land ",
            "optionC": "  Wind ",
            "optionD": "  Ash from volcanoes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor source of oceanic salinity is rivers. There are many chemicals in seawater that make it salty. Most of them get there from rivers carrying chemicals dissolved out of rock and soil. The main one is sodium chloride, often just called salt. ",
            "keyString": "214623s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The deepest trench of the Indian Ocean is",
            "optionA": "  Java Trench ",
            "optionB": "  Aleutian Trench ",
            "optionC": "  Atacama Trench ",
            "optionD": "  Tizard Trench ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe average depth of the Indian Ocean is about 12,750 feet. The deepest is 24,440 feet in the Java Trench in the extreme northeast corner of the basin.",
            "keyString": "214636s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a tropical ocean current?",
            "optionA": "  Curiel ",
            "optionB": "  Canary ",
            "optionC": "  Labrador ",
            "optionD": "  Gulf Stream ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gulf Stream, together with its northern extension the North Atlantic Drift, is a warm and swift Atlantic ocean current that originates in the Gulf of Mexico and stretches to the tip of Florida, and follows the eastern coastlines of the United States and Newfoundland before crossing the Atlantic Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "333187s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Water table' refers to ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The lower limit of the zone of saturation ",
            "optionB": "  The upper limit of the zone of saturation ",
            "optionC": "  The contact zone of permeable and impermeable rocks ",
            "optionD": "  Seepage of water into fissures lying below the earth's surface ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Water table' refers to the upper limit of the zone of saturation. The upper most surface or top level of the zone of saturation is called the water-table. It can also be defined as the level at and below which soil particles are completely saturated. Water table generally follows the relief Unsaturated Zone of the ground.",
            "keyString": "333891s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two main cold currents in the North Pacific Ocean are known as",
            "optionA": "  Oyashio and California currents ",
            "optionB": "  Alaska and Kuroshio currents ",
            "optionC": "  North Equatorial and Counter Equatorial currents ",
            "optionD": "  North Pacific and Kuroshio currents ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo main cold currents in the North Pacific Ocean are known as Oyashio and California currents. The Oyashio cold current is also known as Kurile cold current. This cold current flows through the Bering Strait in southerly direction and thus transports cold water of the Arctic Sea into the Pacific Ocean. Near 50\u00b0N latitude this current is bifurcated into two branches. The California current, an example of cold current, is similar to the Canary cold current of the Atlantic Ocean in most of its characteristics. In fact, this current is the eastward extended portion of the North Pacific drift. ",
            "keyString": "334471s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to a fresh water lake, consider the following characteristics:\n1. Richness in nutrients\n2. Rapid turnover of phytoplankton\n3. Depletion of dissolved oxygen\nWhich of the above is/are observed in a lake after its eutrophication?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDepletion of dissolved oxygen is observed in a lake after its eutrophication. Eutrophication is the process by which a body of water becomes enriched in dissolved nutrients (as phosphates), stimulating the growth of aquatic plant life usually resulting in the depletion of dissolved oxygen.",
            "keyString": "335041s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to Ocean currents consider the following statements:\n1. West Australian current is a warm current.\n2. North East Monsoon Drift flows in the Indian Ocean during winter season.\n3. Equatorial counter current does not flow in the Indian Ocean during winter season.\n4. Kuroshic current in the Pacific Ocean is like Gulf Stream in the Atlantic Ocean.",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth East Monsoon Drift flows in the Indian Ocean during winter season. North-East Monsoon Drift is formed when, in winter, the North-East Monsoon causes a westward and southward drift along the eastern coats of India and along the Arabian coast.. Kuroshic current in the Pacific Ocean is like Gulf Stream in the Atlantic Ocean. The Kuroshio System consists of several currents and drifts is similar to the Gulf Stream system of the Atlantic Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "335666s30m20h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}